Hi everybody, today's י"א Yud Aleph 11, we're a little behind, but
let's be focused, we can maybe, God willing, we will catch up.
So we start at the very last line of י"א עמוד
א'. Yud Amud Aleph. תניא, Tanya, תכוונה למו דרכים. Techavenah lamo derachim.
So in the middle of the creating of the ערי מקלט Arei
Miklat and it says that they would, you know, have the paths
all leading to it. In the משנה Mishnah it sounds like the
paths would interconnect the various ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat, which is not
the most useful. What you really want are paths leading from all
places in the land to the ערי מקלט. Arei Miklat. You know,
what is it, all roads lead to Rome? All roads lead to
ערי מקלט. Arei Miklat. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, ר' אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov Omer, מקלט היה כתוב על הפרשת דרכים. Miklat haya katuv al
haparashat drachim. And at all the crossroads there would always be a
sign saying מקלט Miklat this way. Okay, very helpful, right?
Throughout the country, anytime you got to a crossroads. As Yogi Berra
says, when you come to a fork in the road, take it.
Right? So anyway, so at all the crossroads you would always know
exactly which way to turn to get to the ערי מקלט. Arei
Miklat. כדי שיכיר רוצח ויפנה לשמה. Kedai sheyakir rotzeach viyifneh lishama.
So he should be able to see and turn that way. Again,
it's very interesting that all this person who killed בשוגג B'shogeg is
consistently referred to as רוצח. Rotzeach. אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana,
מאי קרא? Mai Kra? What's the verse that says you have to
do this? תכין לך הדרך. Tachin Lecha Haderech.
So prepare the way. What does it mean prepare the way? עשה
לך הכנה לדרך. Aseh lecha hachanah laderech.
Make the way, you know, direct it and make the way prepared
so that it's easy for him to get there. It also has
to do with road maintenance too. Yeah, that's a good point, road
maintenance is a good point. רב חמא בר חנינא פתח לפתחא להאי
פרשתא מהכא. Rav Chama bar Chanina patach lepitcha lehai parshata meihacha.
So when רב חנינא בר... when רב חמא בר חנינא was going
to דרשן Darshen on the discussion of the ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat,
he would be פותח הפתח, Poteach hapetach, begin his opening from the
following. And this, by the way, is a classic form of Rabbinic
מדרש. Midrash. You see it throughout
בראשית רבה, Bereishit Rabbah, שמות רבה, Shemot Rabbah, the פתיחתא, Petichta, which
is that you usually open from a different פסוק Pasuk and then
you find your way to get to, you know, like if you're
talking in פרשת תולדות, Parshat Toldot, you say like what is it,
עטרת זקנים בני בנים, Ateret zekeinim b'nei banim,
whatever it is. What is it? תפארת
בנים אבותם. Tiferet banim avotam. תפארת בנים אבותם. Tiferet banim avotam. And
then you say so, and then you use that to open and
then that's going to be your... and then somehow you're going to
get to the story of אברהם Avraham and יצחק. Yitzchak. So anyway,
so here too, the idea is how would you... what would you
do your פתיחתא Petichta from? Where would be the פסוקים Pesukim that
you would start from in order to find your way, excuse the
pun anyway, to get your way over to the discussion of ערי
מקלט. Arei Miklat. So רב חמא בר חנינא פתח לפתחא להאי פרשתא
מהכא. Rav Chama bar Chanina patach lepitcha lehai parshata meihacha.
So he would begin it from here. טוב וישר ה' על כן
יורה חטאים בדרך. Tov viyashar Hashem al ken yoreh chataim baderech.
God is right and just and therefore He will show the sinners
the path. So that's obviously the point. Here's somebody who's a sinner,
again, similar to being called a רוצח, Rotzeach, there was negligence led
to the death, it's not a complete accident, and nevertheless God wants
to create the paths in order to protect the sinners and help
them get to the ערי מקלט. Arei Miklat. And then the דרשה
Drasha was אם לחטאים יורה קל וחומר לצדיקים. Im lachataim yoreh kal
vachomer latzadikim. If this is what He does for the wicked, how
much more so to the sinners, how much more so for the
righteous. ריש לקיש פתח לפתחא להאי פרשתא מהכא. Reish Lakish patach lepitcha
lehai parshata meihacha.
He would open the פתיחתא Petichta from the following place: ואשר לא
צדה והאלקים אנה לידו. Va'asher lo tzadah veha'elokim inah leyado.
Now this is actually starting straight with the פסוק. Pasuk. It's not
starting from a distant פסוק Pasuk or some פסוק Pasuk in תנ"ך
Tanach and moving your way, it's starting straight in the פרשה. Parsha.
He would jump straight in. Okay, now, but here's the פסוק Pasuk
that would be a little off topic that he would weave
in: כאשר יאמר משל הקדמני מרשעים יצא רשע. Ka'asher yomar hamashal hakadmoni
meirshaim yeitzei resha.
From wicked people comes out evil. So apparently רש"י Rashi says what's
bothering him in this פסוק Pasuk is ואשר לא צדה והאלקים אנה
לידו, Va'asher lo tzadah veha'elokim inah leyado,
that God made it happen. So it sounds like God made this
person's death happen and the person who killed him was just God's
כלי, Kli, you know, was just the means and God wanted this
death to happen. So if God wanted this death to happen and
God caused it all to happen, why does this guy have to
go into exile? That's the problem, והאלקים אנה לידו. Veha'elokim inah leyado.
So the answer is מרשעים יצא רשע. Meirshaim yeitzei resha.
Evil comes from bad people. This person was evil to begin with
and that's why even though God is manipulating the whole thing, but
ultimately this person goes into exile because he was evil to begin
with. How do we understand what that means? So he says במה
הכתוב מדבר? Bameh hakatuv medaber? What does the verse refer to? בשני
בני אדם שהרגו את הנפש. Bishnei bnei adam shehargu et hanefesh.
Two people who committed murder or killed. אחד הרג בשוגג, Echad harag
bishogeg, one did it unintentionally, ואחד הרג במזיד, V'echad harag bemeizid,
and one did it willfully. וזה אין לו עדים וזה אין לו
עדים. V'zeh ein lo eidim v'zeh ein lo eidim. Neither one have
witnesses. So they both got off scot-free. One's a real murderer, the
other's committed manslaughter and they both got off scot-free. So what's God
going to do? הקדוש ברוך הוא מזמינם לפונדק אחד. Hakadosh Baruch Hu
mazminam lefundak echad.
God makes the events happen so that they both wind up coming
to the same inn. זה שהרג במזיד יושב תחת הסולם. Zeh sheharag
bemeizid yoshev tachat hasulam.
And the one that killed intentionally sits under the ladder. is sitting
under a ladder, וזה שהרג בשוגג יורד בסולם, vezeh sheharag beshogeg yored
basulam,
and the one that killed unintentionally is going down a ladder—notice has
to be going down, remember that—ונפל עליו והרגו, venafal alav vehargo, and
fell on him and killed him. So every justice is served. זה
שהרג במזיד נהרג, zeh sheharag bemeizid neherag, the one who committed who
killed willfully is killed as he would have been executed in a
court, וזה שהרג בשוגג, vezeh sheharag beshogeg, the one who killed unintentionally,
גולה, goleh, goes into exile as he should have been done for
his first act. So therefore God made it happen but ultimately justice
is being served and the guy who goes in exile on the
one hand he was the כלי kli of God and on the
other hand ultimately this is what he had deserved anyway. I mean
I think it's it's worthwhile to point out. Yes. Because I was
looking up in the context of that פסוק pasuk ממרשעים יצא רשע,
mimeresha'im yeitzei resha, it is in the context of David and Shaul
how you know David said I could have killed you Shaul but
I'm not going to. Right. So it's about murder and whatever and
not doing it. Right. Okay, thank you. אמר רבה בר רב הונא
אמר רב הונא ואמרי לה אמר רב הונא אמר רב אלעזר Amar
Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar Rav Huna ve'amri lah amar Rav Huna
amar Rav Elazar מן התורה מן הנביאים ומן הכתובים min haTorah min
haNevi'im umin haKetuvim
we learn out from Torah, Nevi'im, and Ketuvim, בדרך שאדם רוצה לילך
בה מוליכין אותו, bederech she'adam rotzeh lalechet bah molichin oto,
in the path that somebody wants to go, with God you know
they make it possible in heaven or they they send you on
the path that you anyway were going were going. Okay מן התורה
דכתיב min haTorah dechtiv לא תלך עמהם. lo telech imahem.
By by Bilaam it says do not go with them and then
Bilaam insists. So since Bilaam keeps on nudging God, God says וכתיב
קום לך אתם. vechtiv kum lech itam. Fine. You want to go,
go. Okay. That's בדרך שאדם רוצה לילך. bederech she'adam rotzeh lalechet. You
want to go, so God lets you go. God is not going
to stand in your way. מן הנביאים דכתיב min haNevi'im dechtiv אני
ה' אלהיך מלמדך להועיל מדריכך בדרך תלך. Ani Hashem Elohecha melamedcha leho'il
madrichcha bederech telech. I
am Hashem your God teach you for benefit I I
I guide you in the path that you will go. So the
way it's being read is not I I guide you in the
path that you should go, but in the path that you anyway
wanted to go, I will help guide you there. So I you
know if you want to go do evil I'll make it possible.
I you know... But don't we have the whole thing of לפני
עיוור lifnei iver though, like... Well most of this is that God
isn't standing in your way. מן הכתובים דכתיב... min haKetuvim dechtiv... I'm
sorry
I skipped a line. דכתיב אם ללצים הוא יליץ ולענוים יתן חן.
dechtiv im laleitzim hu yalitz vela'anavim yitein chein.
If with the mockers God will be mock and but for the
for the humble God will be gracious. Now what does that show?
So Rashi says it means אם ללצים, im laleitzim,
if somebody who wants to go ahead and be a mocker or
you know do evil, הוא יליץ, hu yalitz, God will make it
possible for him to do so. So God is not going to
stand in the way. Okay God will so this is of course
the idea of דרך, derech, you know, תכין לך הדרך, tachin lecha
haderech, this guy is trying to run to the עיר מקלט ir
miklat and the Torah's making it possible for him to do so,
but now we're obviously using that as a metaphor and also you
know in terms of also bad stuff that God is not going
to stand in the way of somebody who wants... And not only
not standing in his way, telling him to go though, which is
a little bit different. Where? קום לך אתם. kum lech itam. He's
now telling him to go.
He's giving him permission, I don't know. Anyway if you look at
Rashi, הוא יליץ, hu yalitz, אין מעכבין בידו. ein me'akvin beyado. Okay.
אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav Huna: רוצח שגלה לעיר מקלט rotzeiach shegalah
le'ir miklat ומצאו גואל הדם
והרגו פטור. umatzo go'el hadam vehargo patur. Now we're getting into some
הלכה. halacha. So a guy is running to the עיר מקלט ir
miklat and the גואל הדם go'el hadam kills him on the way.
Okay, is he already protected when he's on the way? So he
says the גואל הדם go'el hadam is exempt until he makes it
to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, he's exposed, he's not protected by
law. Okay, פטור, patur, קסבר ולו אין משפט מות בגואל הדם הוא
דכתיב. kasavar velo ein mishpat mavet bigo'el hadam hu dechtiv.
Okay so the פסוק pasuk says right that this person will go
you know to the city to the ערי מקלט arei miklat and
it says פן ירדוף גואל הדם אחרי הרוצח pen yirdof go'el hadam
acharei harotzeiach כי יחם
לבבו והשיגו והרגו בדרך ki yeicham levavo vehisigo vehargo baderech ולו אין
משפט מות velo ein mishpat mavet what?
והשיגו והרגו בדרך vehisigo vehargo baderech
and
so you have to create the ערי מקלט arei miklat lest the
גואל הדם go'el hadam runs after him and kills him on the
way, ולו אין משפט מות כי לא שנא הוא לו מתמול שלשום.
velo ein mishpat mavet ki lo sonei hu lo mitmol shilshom.
And he doesn't deserve to die because he didn't hate him from
the past. So the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is that
the one who killed the person doesn't deserve to die because it
was an unintentional death. Okay? And the פשט pshat of the פסוק
pasuk is now is it now the פסוק pasuk is is seems
to be saying we're creating the ערי מקלט arei miklat to prevent
the גואל הדם go'el hadam from killing him on the way. So
it seems to say that he's protected on the way, right? And
therefore he has to be protected on the way lest the גואל
הדם go'el hadam runs after him and kills him. But this way
is reading it, no, if the גואל הדם go'el hadam succeeds in
killing him on the way, ולו אין משפט מות, velo ein mishpat
mavet,
the גואל הדם go'el hadam is not liable for having killed that
person. Okay because he got him before he got to the עיר
מקלט. ir miklat. And since the גואל הדם go'el hadam will be
exempt before he gets to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, you have
to תכין לך הדרך. tachin lecha haderech. You have to make sure
that the guy can get to the עיר מקלט ir miklat as
quickly as possible. That's a pretty, I mean the problem with... לא
שונא לו מתמול שלשום lo sonei lo mitmol shilshom doesn't fit so
well because that's clearly talking about the guy who did it. But
it's a very reasonable read of the verse, which is, this גואל
הדם goel hadam could kill him before he gets to the ערי
מקלט arei miklat and get away with it. So you have to
do everything you can to make sure he gets to the ערי
מקלט arei miklat as quickly as possible. So that's what he says.
ולא משפט מות, velo mishpat mavet, the גואל הדם goel hadam who
דכתיב, dechtiv,
that's referring to the גואל הדם, goel hadam, he's not liable. מתיב,
meitiv, I'll ask you, ולא משפט מות, velo mishpat mavet, ברוצח הכתוב
מדבר. berotzeach hakatuv medaber.
We have a ברייתא braita that says that's talking about the one
who killed the guy, okay? את אומר ברוצח או אינו אלא בגואל
הדם, at omer berotzeach o eino ela begoel hadam,
maybe it's referring to the גואל הדם goel hadam that he's not
liable while the guy's on the way? כשהוא אומר keshehu omer והוא
לא שונא לו מתמול שלשום, vehu lo sonei lo mitmol shilshom, he
didn't hate him from the past, הוי אומר ברוצח הכתוב מדבר. hevei
omer berotzeach hakatuv medaber.
That's clearly talking about the guy who killed them and saying that
it was unintentional because he didn't hate this guy who died. He
says it twice, לא שונא לו. lo sonei lo. I understand. Okay,
so the גמרא gemara says, so you see that according to this
ברייתא, braita, it's not set about the גואל הדם. goel hadam. So
הוא דאמר, hu de'amar, this position goes like the one that says
כי האי תנא, ki hai tanna, like the following תנא, tanna, דתניא,
detanya, ולא משפט מות, velo mishpat mavet, בגואל הדם הכתוב מדבר. begoel
hadam hakatuv medaber. There's a תנא tanna that
says it is referring to the גואל הדם, goel hadam, that he's
not liable if he kills the guy on the way. את אומר
בגואל הדם הכתוב מדבר או אינו אלא ברוצח, at omer begoel hadam
hakatuv medaber o eino ela berotzeach,
maybe it's referring to the murderer or the killer? כשהוא אומר keshehu
omer כי לא שונא לו מתמול שלשום, ki lo sonei lo mitmol
shilshom, the end of the פסוק, pasuk, לא שונא לו מתמול שלשום,
lo sonei lo mitmol shilshom, it's a bit ironic,
that is clearly talking about the guy who killed and that he
is and that he is not sort of, you know, to be
treated as a murderer, he did not do it intentionally. So since
that last phrase is talking about the guy who killed, the previous
phrase ולא משפט מות velo mishpat mavet would be redundant if it
was talking about the guy who killed. So the previous phrase ולא
משפט מות velo mishpat mavet clearly is talking about the גואל הדם
goel hadam according to this. So you mean there's a different, he
has a better interpretation of this? Of the גמרא? gemara? Yeah, the
way... Okay, one minute, let me finish reading it. או אינו אלא
ברוצח כשהוא אומר כי לא שונא... o eino ela berotzeach keshehu omer
ki lo sonei... הוי רוצח אמור. hevei rotzeach emor. הא מני מקיים
ולא משפט מות? ha mani mekayem velo mishpat mavet? בגואל הדם הכתוב
מדבר. begoel hadam hakatuv medaber. So it's talking about the גואל הדם.
goel hadam.
So we have this very critically important debate whether when the תורה
torah says he is not liable for death, is it referring to
the one who's running away and that he's protected while he's running
to the ערי מקלט, arei miklat, or does it mean that the
גואל הדם goel hadam won't be liable for death? And because of
that, you have to make, you have to ensure that this guy
can get to the עיר מקלט ir miklat as quickly as possible.
Yes. Because I think what the גמרא gemara is trying to say
is that in פסוק ד pasuk daled you have וזה דבר הרוצח
אשר ינוס שמה וחי אשר יכה את רעהו בבלי דעת והוא לא
שונא לו מתמול שלשום. veze devar harotzeach asher yanus shamma vachai asher
yakeh et re'ehu bivli daat vehu lo sonei lo mitmol shilshom.
Right.
So that first part is clearly רוצח rotzeach because it's all... Oh,
so you mean the whole לא שונא לו lo sonei lo in
that first part is talking about the רוצח? rotzeach? Maybe. Could be.
Okay, so then later when they say oh, it's the same one
we're talking about before. So that's the first opinion, it's talking about
the רוצח. rotzeach. Second one is, no, since you already talked about
the רוצח rotzeach in the first part, the second time they say
it, they're talking about different... Oh, I hear, I hear. Okay, so
that the לא שונא לו lo sonei lo is going about the
earlier reference to it. That could be. Okay, let's go on.
Anyway, you have this critical debate whether the person is protected on
the way. I actually think פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, although
לא שונא לו lo sonei lo and ולא משפט מות, velo mishpat
mavet, I do think פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is referring
to the guy who killed, but I think that the idea that
the גואל הדם goel hadam can kill him with impunity until he
gets to the עיר מקלט ir miklat is פשט pshat of the
פסוקים. psukim. And that's why the פסוקים psukim say תכין לך הדרך.
tachin lecha haderech. You've got to make sure because lest the guy,
he's exposed before he gets to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat.
Exactly. Well, that's what the גמרא gemara is now going to deal
with. Okay, תנן. tnan. So now let's see if we can sort
of figure this out based on a משנה. mishna.
תנן: tnan: מוסרין לו שני תלמידי חכמים שמא יהרגנו בדרך וידברו אליו.
mosrin lo shnei talmidei chachamim shema yehargenu baderech veyedabru elav. So you
have these two תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim to talk to the גואל
הדם. goel hadam. So מאי לאו, mai lav, what are they going
to say to him? So if they're תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, presumably
the reason is to talk הלכה. halacha. So they're דמסהדי ביה, demas'hadei
beih, they'll give him התראה, hasraah, דאי קטיל בר קטלא הוא. de'i
katil bar ktola hu. And they'll tell him if you kill this
guy, you're going to be liable the death penalty. So that's why
you need תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. This proves that the person is
protected along the way. And that's what the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim
are there to do, is to tell the גואל הדם goel hadam
that he's protected and that he could, he would be committing murder.
So no, no, maybe it just means they'll be just persuasive. Maybe
it does not mean they're going to talk הלכה. halacha. לא. lo.
I understand. כדתניא, kedatanya, וידברו אליו דברים ראוים לו. veyedabru elav devarim
re'uyim lo. You speak to him things that he's able to hear.
אומרים לו, omrim lo, אל תנהג בו מנהג שופכי דמים, al tinhag
bo minhag shofchei damim, hey, don't kill this guy, don't treat him
like a murderer. בשגגה בא לידו, bishgaga ba leyado,
the whole thing was an accident. Okay, and of course as Mike
says, good luck with that with a גואל הדם goel hadam who's
running in his heat of passion and you say to him, oh,
you know, it was just an accident. Okay, and why do you
need תלמידי חכמים? talmidei chachamim? But maybe the גמרא gemara assumes that
תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, maybe they have a certain authority to them,
you know, maybe they can speak in a certain like nuanced way.
Okay, but yes, this is the issue. Are they telling him הלכה?
halacha? Hey, you should know the guy is protected, you'll be committing
murder, or are they just trying to persuade him? Okay, רבי מאיר
אומר Rabbi Meir omer הוא מדבר על ידי עצמו. hu medaber al
yedei atzmo. He's even, he can even or should even, could even
talk for himself. שנאמר וזה דבר... shene'emar veze devar... the word of
the רוצח. rotzeach. אמרו לו, Amru lo, so the rabbis said back
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, הרבה שליחות עושה. harbei shlichut oseh. You
know what, having somebody speak for you, having an emissary can accomplish
a lot that you can't accomplish yourself. So it's very important, right,
especially if you're trying to defend your own life and saying, hey,
you know, here's the guy who killed, you know, your relative and
he's trying to convince you not to kill him, right? It's probably
not going to be so successful. Okay, so it's very often very
helpful to have an intermediary rather than to try to do it
yourself. So anyway, it does not seem that that's, so this is
a halakhic debate. אמר מר, Amar mar, בשגגה בא מידו. bishgaga ba
miyado. So what they say to the גואל הדם goel hadam is
hey, you should know this was just an accident. פשיטא, Peshita, דבמזיד
בר גלותא הוא, de'be'mezid bar galuta hu, obviously, because otherwise דבמזיד בר
גלותא הוא, de'be'mezid bar galuta hu, obviously this was an accident because
if it wasn't intentional you think the guy would be going to
the עיר מקלט? ir miklat? Right, the point is, it's not like
it's an intellectual point that you're making with גואל הדם, goel hadam,
it's a persuasion point. Okay, but the גמרא gemara asks והא במזיד,
v'has be'mezid, so the guy is...
That's also true. Wait, and then everyone went to the עיר מקלט...
ir miklat... Well, that's the גמרא's gemara answer. The גמרא gemara says
אין, In, yes, maybe the גואל הדם goel hadam thinks that this
guy is a מזיד mezid and maybe they actually are not just
persuading the גואל הדם goel hadam but informing him that he's a
שוגג. shogeg. Why? דתניא, Detanya, because we taught in a ברייתא, braita,
everybody goes to the עיר מקלט ir miklat initially. So it could
be he's running to the עיר מקלט ir miklat and he is
a מזיד. mezid. רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר בתחילה אחד, Rabbi Yose
bar Yehuda omer bit'chilla echad,
the first thing we would do is אחד שוגג ואחד מזיד מקדימין
לעיר מקלט. echad shogeg ve'echad mezid makdimin le'ir miklat. You send everybody
to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. ובית דין שולחים ומביאים אותם משם,
U'bet din sholchim u'mivi'im otam misham,
and בית דין bet din then, you know, they take control of
the whole thing and then they recall the people from the עיר
מקלט. ir miklat. It's like a jail. מי שנתחייב מיתה הרגו, Mi
she'nitchayav mita haragu,
the person who then is found guilty of murder is executed. שנאמר
ושלחו זקני עירו ולקחו אותו משם ונתנו אותו ביד גואל הדם ומת.
Shene'emar ve'shalchu ziknei iro ve'lakchu oto misham ve'natnu oto beyad goel hadam
va'met.
Of course, the פשט pshat of those פסוקים psukim is the גואל
הדם goel hadam kills him, so there's still some maintenance of vigilante
justice under the control of בית דין, bet din, but of course
that's not הלכה halakha what we do. The בית דין bet din
executes him. מי שלא נתחייב פטרוהו, Mi she'lo nitchayav patruhu,
if somebody was completely innocent, you know, is either total אונס onnes
or maybe he didn't even do it, so then they just free
him. שנאמר והצילו העדה את הרוצח מיד גואל הדם. Shene'emar ve'hitzilu ha'eda
et harotzeach miyad goel hadam.
They free him. מי שנתחייב גלות מחזירין אותו למקומו, Mi she'nitchayav galut
machzirin oto limkomo, and the person who killed but it was בשוגג,
beshogeg,
they send him back to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. שנאמר והשיבו
אותו העדה אל עיר מקלטו אשר נס שמה. Shene'emar ve'heshivu oto ha'eda
el ir miklato asher nas shamma. Okay. So basically, so yes, part
of the thing is that תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim have to do
is not just persuade but also inform. You should know this guy,
yes it's true he killed your brother or whatever, but it was
an accident. Wait, so they say it all the time then? Even
if it was a מזיד, mezid, right? What? They say it all
the time? No, I don't think that you have the תלמידי חכמים,
talmidei chachamim, it's a good point, but I don't think you have
the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim you send the guy to the עיר
מקלט, ir miklat, but how do you know if it's a מזיד
mezid or a שוגג? shogeg? Well, if there's no תלמידי חכמים, talmidei
chachamim, then you can... No, but how do the תלמידי חכמים talmidei
chachamim know? Yeah, that I was wondering too. You have to have
like a presumption of what happened before you actually have the court
case. I do understand. I assume the case is that at any
time בית דין bet din thinks that there's, you know, that thinks
that it could be a שוגג, shogeg, they would tell him it's
a שוגג, shogeg, but I was wondering the same thing. Yeah. If
it went through a court and it was a מזיד, mezid, then
he wouldn't be able to run to the... No, this is way
before it's gone to the court. Reuven kills Shimon, okay? Now he
runs to the עיר מקלט ir miklat to wait until the trial.
Yes, as he's running to the עיר מקלט ir miklat to wait
until the trial, the גואל הדם's goel hadam running after him. So
Michael says, okay, how do the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim know to
tell the גואל הדם goel hadam he's a שוגג shogeg not a
מזיד mezid if we haven't had the trial yet? So I assume
though that they would say based on the presumption of what we
know right now, or if it looks like it's possible it was
a שוגג, shogeg, that's what they would tell him. But if they're
going to trial... Yeah, but that's not what the ברייתא braita says.
The ברייתא braita says they tell him, hey, don't kill him, he
was a שוגג. shogeg. You know, of course the question is that
would they, you know, it's an interesting question as well, which thank
you, which I thought Michael was asking, which is, would they also
want to say
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim to protect even the מזיד mezid guy? Right.
Right, because you want to still, you want the court to deal
with it, you don't want the גואל הדם goel hadam to deal
with it. Okay. So anyway, the גמרא gemara says like this.
Okay. רבי אומר מעצמן הן גולים. Rabbi omer me'atzman hen golim. Now
רבי Rabbi says, no, no, no. That's not...
That's not the פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. פשט pshat of
the פסוקים psukim is not that בית דין bet din sends the
מזיד mezid to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. Yes, the פסוקים psukim
do say explicitly that the בית דין bet din will send to
the עיר מקלט ir miklat to get the guy to come and
then they'll execute him if he did it במזיד. bemezid. So the
פסוקים psukim do describe a scenario where a מזיד mezid guy went
to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. But רבי Rabbi says that was
not under בית דין's bet din authority. The guy just ran on
his own to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. If בית דין bet
din is controlling it, then the מזיד mezid guys, they'll just keep,
right, you know, I don't know, local to the court. Maybe some
jail in the court or whatever they'll do, but he won't go
to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. Okay. So when the מזיד mezid
goes to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, that was his own decision.
מעצמן הן גולים. Me'atzman hen golim. סוברים הן אחד שוגג ואחד מזיד
קולטת. Soverin hen echad shogeg ve'echad mezid koletet. They think, the ones
who killed במזיד, bemezid, that the עיר מקלט ir miklat protects a
person whether they're שוגג shogeg or
מזיד. mezid. ואינן יודעים שבשוגג קולטת ובמזיד אינה קולטת. Ve'einan yodim she'bashogeg
koletet u'vemezid einam koletet. But it actually does not protect the intentional
murderer. So here you have a fascinating debate of how to read
the פסוקים psukim and it seems like it's also... debate about whether
is the guy who killed במזיד b'meizid protected as long as he's
in the עיר מקלט ir miklat until the trial can be held,
or does the גואל הדם goel hadam able to enter into the
עיר מקלט ir miklat and kill the guy who killed במזיד b'meizid
and get off scot-free? Of course, as Michael points out, the whole
question is how do you determine whether the גואל הדם goel hadam
what he did was right or not right and whether the עיר
מקלט ir miklat was protecting or not protecting if you haven't had
the trial yet? Maybe you have the trial after the guy's already
after the, you know, the רוצח rotzeach is already dead. I don't
know. And then he can't defend himself. I understand.
It's very strange, I agree. Okay.
אמר רבי אלעזר עיר שרובה רוצחים אינה קולטת. Amar Rabbi Elazar: Ir
she-rubah rotzchim einah koletet. Let's say your עיר מקלט, ir miklat, you
know, your עיר מקלט ir miklat is supposed to be—I said a
minute ago jail, but I only meant that it was functioning that
way in the interim. But obviously from the earlier גמרא, Gemara, we
see that you have a vibrant city. It's not a huge city,
a vibrant town. And one of the functions it does is it
serves as a sanctuary city. Okay, but if it happens that everybody
in the town, a majority of the people in the town, are
these people who killed בשוגג, bi-shogeg, it stops functioning. Okay? You need
sort of the normal people to give it a status of a
town that then protects the minority population
that are the people who killed. שנאמר ודיבר באזני
זקני העיר ההיא את דבריו. shene'emar: v'diber b'oznei ziknei ha'ir ha'hi et
devarav. This is in יהושע, Yehoshua, where it talks about the עיר
מקלט. ir miklat. And he'll speak in the ears of the elders
of that city. שלא הושוו דבריו לדבריהם. lo she-hushu devav l'dvarav. It
means that they are distinct from him, from the guy who committed
murder. Not like they're all in the same category. ואמר רבי אלעזר
עיר שאין בה זקנים אינה קולטת. V'amar Rabbi Elazar: Ir she-ein bah
zekeinim einah koletet. If there are no elders, it doesn't work. דבעינן
זקני העיר וליכא. d'beinan ziknei ha'ir v'leika. These פסוקים pesukim in יהושע
Yehoshua tell us the criteria of what you need for an עיר
מקלט, ir miklat, and you need there to be elders. איתמר עיר
שאין בה זקנים. Itmar: Ir she-ein bah zekeinim. Now this is actually
debated. רב אמי ורב אסי. Rav Ami v'Rav Assi. חד אמר קולטת.
chad amar koletet. One says—it's debated of רב אמי ורב אסי—one Rav
Ami v'Rav Assi says it still protects, וחד אמר אינה קולטת, v'chad
amar einah koletet, it doesn't. למאן דאמר אינה קולטת בעינן זקני העיר.
Le-man d'amar einah koletet: beinan ziknei ha'ir. That's the verse in יהושע.
Yehoshua. It mentions the elders. וליכא, v'leika, and you don't have it.
למאן דאמר קולטת מצוה בעלמא. Le-man d'amar koletet: mitzva b'alma. That's just
describing the ideal, but it's not really describing what is absolutely necessary.
It's not מעכב, me'akev, as we would say. עיר שאין בה זקנים.
Ir she-ein bah zekeinim. Similarly, if the city has no elders. רב
אמי ורב אסי. Rav Ami v'Rav Assi. Same debate. חד אמר נעשה
בה בן סורר ומורה. chad amar na'aseh bah ben sorer u'moreh. A
child can become a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh in such
a city. Fascinating. We had this in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. וחד אמר אי
נעשה בה בן סורר ומורה. v'chad amar ei na'aseh bah ben sorer
u'moreh. Can't. למאן דאמר אי נעשה בן סורר ומורה, Le-man d'amar ei
na'aseh ben sorer u'moreh, you can't make a child a בן סורר
ומורה ben sorer u'moreh in such a town. בעינן זקני עירו beinan
ziknei iro because it says the parents take him to the elders.
וליכא. v'leika. למאן דאמר נעשה בן סורר ומורה מצוה בעלמא. Le-man d'amar
na'aseh ben sorer u'moreh: mitzva b'alma. No, that's just saying that that
would be the best way to do it. But if there are
no elders, you take him to the בית דין Beit Din of
the next town. They don't need it to be the בית דין
Beit Din of this town. ועיר שאין בה זקנים. v'ir she-ein bah
zekeinim. And similarly if there's no elders, meaning like no בית דין.
Beit Din. רב אמי ורב אסי. Rav Ami v'Rav Assi. חד אמר
מביאה עגלה ערופה. chad amar mevi'ah eglah arufah. If there's a suspicious
death outside the city. So,
and it says that the elders come, you know, and they make
this whole declaration and they lead the whole ritual of the עגלה
ערופה. eglah arufah. But one says even without elders, you can do
it. וחד אמר אינה מביאה עגלה ערופה. v'chad amar einah mevi'ah eglah
arufah. I don't know who would do it. You would appoint some,
I don't know, some laypeople as leaders or something? I don't know.
למאן דאמר אינה מביאה עגלה ערופה. Le-man d'amar einah mevi'ah eglah arufah.
It doesn't bring it. בעינן זקני העיר ההיא וליכא. beinan ziknei ha'ir
ha'hi v'leika. Makes a lot of sense there in particular. Right? Because
there it's like it's about the city taking responsibility. It's one thing
by the בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u'moreh, you say okay, go
to the בית דין Beit Din in the next town. But here
the whole point is the city takes responsibility and the whole ritual
is with the זקנים. zekeinim. So you know, who else is going
to do it? Do they say, you know, presumably some lay leader
or something? למאן דאמר מביאה עגלה ערופה מצוה בעלמא. Le-man d'amar mevi'ah
eglah arufah: mitzva b'alma. Just a מצוה. mitzva. Now תוספות Tosafot says,
what do you mean מצוה בעלמא? mitzva b'alma? There's a גמרא Gemara
that says that if you have surrounding towns and one, and the
closest one doesn't have elders and a further town has elders, it's
the further town that has the elders that does the עגלה ערופה.
eglah arufah. So clearly you need elders. So תוספות Tosafot says no,
that's just when you can choose. If you can choose between a
town that has elders and one that doesn't, you give the ritual
to the town that does, although they might not be the responsible
town. But if all the surrounding towns don't have elders, then you
go forth with the ritual without the elders. Okay. אמר רבי חמא
בר חנינא מפני
מה נאמר פרשת רוצחים בלשון עזה? Amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina: mipnei
mah ne'emar parashat rotzchim bi-lashon azah? Why, when it says in יהושע
Yehoshua top of י"א עמוד א', yud-alef amud alef, the story about
the murderer, about the רוצח, rotzeach, right, about the עיר מקלט, ir
miklat, that it speaks in a harsh language? A harsh language is
because in all of ספר יהושע, Sefer Yehoshua, when God speaks to
יהושע, Yehoshua, it says ויאמר, va-yomer, God said. But when it says,
when it speaks about this issue, it says וידבר, va-yidaber, God spoke.
And you know, I'm even like just hearing the, you know, the
way the word sounds. ד-ב-ר. da-ber. What are those called? Gutturals? Not
gutturals. B, B. Whatever. What? Something. Anyway, you hear it's the harder
word. Anyway, and חז"ל Chazal understood that that always meant a harsher
form of speech. So why is it? דכתיב וידבר ה' אל יהושע
לאמר. d'chtiv: va-yidaber Hashem el Yehoshua leimor. It says, look how many
times it says the word דבר. daber. Nowhere else in יהושע. Yehoshua.
דבר אל בני ישראל לאמר תנו לכם את ערי המקלט אשר דברתי
אליכם. Daber el bnei yisrael leimor: tnu lachem et arei hamiklat asher
dibarti aleichem. דבר, daber, דבר, daber, דבר. daber. Now, of course, the
first answer, which I think is a very good פשט pshat answer:
מפני שהן של תורה. mipnei she-hen shel Torah. Because you're doing a
מצוה mitzva in the תורה, Torah, right? וידבר ה'. va-yidaber Hashem. classically
evokes וידבר השם אל משה לאמר, Vayidaber Hashem el Moshe lemor, right?
ואשר דבר אל בני ישראל, va-asher daber el Bnei Yisrael, אשר דברתי.
asher dibarti. So it's evoking the fact that this is a fulfillment
of the mitzvah of the Torah. Now the harshness might be because
like you know he really wants to make sure that he takes
it seriously or that he's really on top of it. Okay? It's
very weighty. מפני שהן של תורה, mipnei she-hen shel Torah, למימרא דכל
דיבור לשון קשה? lememra de-chol dibur lashon kasha? Are you telling me
every time it says וידבר vayidaber it's harsh? אין כדכתיב in kidechtiv
דבר האיש אדוני הארץ אתנו קשות. diber ha-ish adonei ha-aretz itanu kashot.
The man, the head of the land, Yosef, spoke with us harshly.
והתניא va-hatanya אז נדברו יראי השם, az nidberu yirei Hashem, right? ואין
נדברו אלא לשון נחת, ve-ein nidberu ella lashon nachas, that means pleasantly.
וכן הוא אומר ve-chein hu omer ידבר עמים תחתינו, yadber amim tachtenu,
to lead nations, to lead you know under us. So it's a
nice, pleasant, it's being led. I'm sorry, so that's like a nice
pleasant thing. Yes, yeah, so the context of תחתינו tachtenu is not
pleasant, but ידבר yadber is, what can I say? I don't want
to debate it. אלא, ella, אלא, ella, so the גמרא Gemara says
דיבור לחוד ידבר לחוד. dibur lachud yadber lachud. No, דיבור, dibur, speech,
is harsh; ידבר, yadber, to lead, might be more pleasant. Anyway, פליגי
רבי יהודה ורבנן. peligi Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbanan. חד אמר משום שהיהם. chad
amar mishum she-hiham. No, the reason is the harshness is not because
it's biblical and it's weighty, but because Yehoshua carried in fulfilling the
mitzvah, so God was angry with Yehoshua. וחד אמר מפני שהן של
תורה, ve-chad amar mipnei she-hen shel Torah, what we said before, because
it's biblical. Okay, ויכתוב יהושע את הדברים האלה בספר תורת אלוהים. Vayichtov
Yehoshua et ha-devarim ha-eleh be-sefer Torat Elohim. Now since we're talking about
Yehoshua let's talk about another interesting question about a pasuk in יהושע
Yehoshua which also connects to ערי מקלט. arei miklat. ויכתוב יהושע את
הדברים האלה בספר תורת אלוהים. Vayichtov Yehoshua et ha-devarim ha-eleh be-sefer Torat
Elohim. Yehoshua wrote these words, again notice the word דברים, devarim, in
the book of the Torah of God. So it sounds like the
ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So פליגי רבי יהודה ורבי נחמיה. peligi Rabbi
Yehuda ve-Rabbi Nechemya. חד אמר שמונה פסוקים. chad amar shemona pesukim. So
this is great. The last eight pesukim of the Torah where we
had a debate in בבא בתרא Bava Batra whether Moshe wrote them
or Yehoshua wrote them, because who wrote from the time it says
משה מת? Moshe met? Did Moshe write משה מת Moshe met and
the last eight pesukim in the Torah? So there's an opinion that
Yehoshua wrote them. So we're tying it into a pasuk in יהושע
Yehoshua that says that יהושע Yehoshua wrote words in the ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah. So what better words could those refer to than the
last eight פסוקים pesukim of the Torah in דברים? Devarim? Oh, also
הדברים. ha-devarim. I wasn't thinking about that, but also in ספר דברים.
Sefer Devarim. Right, right, right, הדברים האלה. ha-devarim ha-eleh. You're right, it's
ספר דברים, Sefer Devarim, I wasn't even thinking about that. So it's
perfect, it ties it all in a nice little bow. וחד אמר,
ve-chad amar, no, וחד אמר פרשת ערי מקלט. ve-chad amar parshat arei
miklat. It doesn't mean that he, now it doesn't mean he wrote
the parsha of ערי מקלט. arei miklat. If you look at רש"י,
Rashi, it says וחד אמר פרשת ערי מקלט הוא אומר שכתובה בספר
יהושע. ve-chad amar parshat arei miklat hu omer she-ketuva be-sefer Yehoshua. I
think רש"י Rashi is saying, I think רש"י Rashi is saying that
the ספר תורת אלוהים Sefer Torat Elohim is not referring to the
ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, it's referring to ספר יהושע, Sefer Yehoshua, okay?
That's the way I'm reading רש"י. Rashi. I don't think we're saying
that יהושע Yehoshua went back and wrote ערי מקלט arei miklat in
the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. We're saying that יהושע Yehoshua went back,
right, רש"י Rashi says שכתובה בספר יהושע. she-ketuva be-sefer Yehoshua. The ספר
תורת אלוהים Sefer Torat Elohim here is יהושע, Yehoshua, it's not the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah of משה. Moshe. Okay. Now, בשלמא למאן דאמר
ח' פסוקים היינו דכתיב בספר תורת אלוהים. bishlama le-man de-amar chet pesukim
haynu de-chtiv be-sefer Torat Elohim. Oh yeah, it's right in the גמרא.
Gemara. That's the ספר תורת אלוהים, Sefer Torat Elohim, that's the, you
know, תורת משה, Torat Moshe, what we call the ספר תורה. Sefer
Torah. אלא למאן דאמר ערי מקלט מאי בספר תורת אלוהים? ella le-man
de-amar arei miklat mai be-sefer Torat Elohim? What does it mean ספר
תורת אלוהים Sefer Torat Elohim if it was only the book of
יהושע Yehoshua that he wrote it? הכי קאמר ויכתוב יהושע בספרו את
הדברים האלה הכתובים בספר תורת אלוהים. hachi ka-amar vayichtov Yehoshua be-sifro et
ha-devarim ha-eleh ha-ketuvim be-sefer Torat Elohim. He wrote the words that are
in the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and he wrote the fulfillment of
that command in his book, in ספר יהושע. Sefer Yehoshua. Okay. Now
another debate since we have this idea of debate of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and X, חד אמר chad amar this and חד אמר
chad amar this, we're going to have a few others, not exactly
related. ספר שתפרו בפשתן. Sefer she-tefaro be-pishtan. Let's say you have a
ספר תורה Sefer Torah that you tied the pieces of parchment together
with flax instead of with גידים, gidim, instead of with like, what,
sinews, right? They're made from like intestines or whatever, which is what
we normally do. פליגי רבי יהודה ורבי מאיר. peligi Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi
Meir. It's a debate. חד אמר כשר, chad amar kasher, it's kosher,
וחד אמר פסול, ve-chad amar pasul, it's pasul. מאן דאמר פסול דכתיב
למען תהיה תורת השם בפיך. man de-amar pasul de-chtiv le-maan tihye Torat
Hashem be-ficha. That we learn that the contents of the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah have to be from things that are kosher to eat.
So now of course it's not that it's not kosher to eat
flax, but that sort of tells you that it's sort of from
animal products and kosher animal products. והקיש, ve-hikish, and so we learn
that, and that also actually, I'm sorry, I said that wrong. That's
by תפילין. tefillin. By תפילין tefillin it says that you have to
put on תפילין tefillin למען תהיה תורת השם בפיך, le-maan tihye Torat
Hashem be-ficha, okay? And that פסוק pasuk that connects תפילין tefillin to
תורה, Torah, תורת השם, Torat Hashem, right, is how we say that
all the הלכות halachot that we know by תפילין tefillin apply by
ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So that's the point. That תורת השם Torat
Hashem there connects תפילין tefillin to ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, and we
know הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai that תפילין tefillin have to
be sewn together like with with גידין, giddin, so therefore, here too
we learn that it requires גידין. giddin. So והקיש כל התורה כולה
לתפילין, vehikish kol haTorah kulla l'tefillin, מה תפילין הלכה למשה מסיני לתופרן
בגידין, mah tefillin Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai l'tofran b'giddin, the same way by
תפילין tefillin that's the הלכה halacha that you use גידין, giddin, אף
כל לתופרן בגידין, af kol l'tofran b'giddin, the same is true by
ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. ואידך, ve'idach, and the other view says no,
כי הקיש ל"למען תהיה תורת ה' בפיך" להלכותיו לא הקיש. ki hikish
l'"L'ma'an tihiye Toras Hashem beficha" l'hilchosav lo hikish. So no, you only
connect it to the תורה Torah for the דרשה drasha of בפיך.
beficha. The בפיך beficha דרשה drasha is is that the parchment that
you use has to be from a kosher animal, למותר בפיך, limutar
beficha, something that you can put in your mouth. So yes, למען
תהיה תורת ה' בפיך L'ma'an tihiye Toras Hashem beficha connects תפילין tefillin
to ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, but only for the הלכה halacha that
the קלף klaf has to be made from the parchment of a
kosher animal. For other הלכות, halachos, for other details, they are not
connected. And therefore, even though תפילין tefillin requires גידין, giddin, like this
cat you know what's it called sinews or whatever, so but a
ספר sefer but a ספר תורה Sefer Torah does not. לא הקיש.
lo hikish. אמר רב חזינא, Amar Rav Chazina, said רב חזינא, Rav
Chazina, חזינא להו לתפילין דבי חביבי, chazeina lehu l'tefillin d'bei chavivi, I
saw the תפילין tefillin in my the house of my beloved, which
is רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, דתפירי בכיתנא, detfiri bechitna, that they were
sewn together with flax. Now that's nobody says that's okay because that's
that's תפילין. tefillin. ולית הלכתא כוותיה, v'leis hilchasa kevasei, that is not
the הלכה. halacha. פשיטא, Pshita, moving on to the next משנה. mishnah.
אחד משוח בשמן המשחה ואחד המרובה בבגדים, Echad mashuach b'shemen hamishcha v'echad
hamerubeh b'v'gadim, now we're going to talk now that we've talked about
him getting to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, now we're going to
talk about the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dying. And who is the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that whose death frees the the the person
who went to the עיר מקלט? ir miklat? So whether it was
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who was anointed with the oil of
the שמן המשחה, shemen hamishcha, which was in the first בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, ואחד המרובה בבגדים v'echad hamerubeh b'v'gadim or was the one
that his the way he became כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was that
he wore the special eight garments of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
but not with the oil, that happened towards the end of the
first בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, they lost the שמן המשחה, shemen hamishcha,
so the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol only became invested through the wearing
of the garments. ואחד שעבר ממשיחותו, v'echad she'avar mimishichuso, even somebody who
was a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who actually for a period was
retired, or not retired whatever, like he had some פסול psul and
he couldn't serve and it was יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, maybe he
had had a seminal emission and somebody else served in his place.
So now you have like a sitting כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and
an ex-כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So even if you're just an ex-כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, that person's death would free the גואל הדם. goel
hadam. מחזירין את הרוצח, Machzirin es harotzeach, they would all bring him
back. רבי יהודה אומר אף משוח מלחמה מחזיר את הרוצח, Rabbi Yehuda
omer af mashuach milchama machzir es harotzeach, even the guy who's anointed
as the כהן Kohen to lead the people into war because that's,
you know, in some places the תורה Torah sort of speaks about
him being anointed and having a lofty status over other כהנים, kohanim,
so that would include even his. לפיכך, Lefikach, now, whatever whichever כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol it is, because the death of the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol frees this guy, אמותיהם של כהנים מספקות להן מחיה וכסות,
imoseihem shel kohanim mesapkos lahen michya u'chsus, the mothers of the כהנים
גדולים kohanim gedolim would readily send care packages, you know, to the
רוצחים rotzchim in the ערי מקלט. arei miklat. Okay? כדי שלא יתפללו
על בניהם שימותו, k'dei shelo yispallelu al beneihem sheyamusu, she's like you
know, don't pray for our kids to die. So our son, you
know, don't pray for my son to die because, you know, here
you are, you're waiting to go free, so you're waiting for the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to die. So the mothers would be very
nice to you, you know, and then you'd say, "Well, if he
dies, you you just feel maybe gratitude, she gave me all this
nice טשולנט cholent and food and whatever, now I'm going to wish
death on her son? She's such a lovely woman." Okay, but the
other thing is also like if I maybe now if I if
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies, I have to leave this עיר
מקלט, ir miklat, I'm going to stop getting all these care packages.
You know, so anyway, so anyway, that's what they would do. It's
also wonderful the sense that, you know, that there's a sort of
belief in the efficacy of prayer, right? That it's you know, just
their concern about the prayers and what the effect the prayers will
have. All right, let's right? Yeah, this is just amazing. All focused
on this point. Once they've been in the עיר מקלט ir miklat
and left, does that mean the גואל הדם goel hadam can't get
them anymore? Correct. Then they're like protected like anybody else. That is
correct. Okay, which doesn't mean the גואל הדם goel hadam won't kill
them, but legally they're protected. מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei mili? Where
is this from? אמר רב כהנא דאמר קרא, Amar Rav Kahana d'amar
kra, that all these different are people are considered כהנים גדולים, kohanim
gedolim, that it includes all these כהנים גדולים. kohanim gedolim. אמר רב
כהנא דאמר קרא וישב בה עד מות הכהן הגדול, Amar Rav Kahana
d'amar kra v'yashav bah ad mos hakohen hagadol, וכתיב כי בעיר מקלטו
ישב עד מות הכהן הגדול, u'chsiv ki b'ir miklato yeshev ad mos
hakohen hagadol, וכתיב אחרי מות הכהן הגדול. u'chsiv acharei mos hakohen hagadol.
Three times it says the word כהן הגדול, Kohen HaGadol, so to
include three variations of a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. ולרבי יהודה U'l'Rabbi
Yehuda who has a fourth variation, משוח מלחמה, mashuach milchama, כתיב קרא
אחרינא לשוב לשבת בארץ עד מות הכהן. ksiv kra achrina lashuv lasheves
ba'aretz ad mos hakohen. Okay, so it's once again mentions כהן. Kohen.
ואידך, V'idach, מדלא כתיב הגדול, midelo ksiv hagadol, it doesn't say the
כהן הגדול, Kohen HaGadol, חד מהנך, chad mehanch, it means one of
the three כהנים גדולים kohanim gedolim we mentioned before. It's not coming
to include a fourth variation of who's a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
פשיטא לפיכך אמותיהם של כהנים. Pshita lefikach imoseihem shel kohanim. So the
mothers would make all these nice care packages. Or I mean, if
you have I guess you have a but it's funny it says
the mothers, because in any one time, I mean, you're you well
you could have up to three. You won't have a משוח mashuach
and מרובה בבגדים, merubeh b'v'gadim, right, in the you would have... and
you could have a מרובה בגדים Merubeh Begadim and you could have
an ex כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and you could have a משוח
מלחמה. Mashuach Milchama. So you could have up to three at any
one time. Okay. Now, טעמא דלא מצלו, taima d'lo matslu, so the
reason that they're not going to that that they won't die is
because they're not being prayed that they should die. המצלו מייתי, Hamatslu
meiti, which means the implication of the mishna is, as I said,
the efficacy of prayer, that were they to be praying that the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would die, that might bring about his death.
דכתיב, Dechtiv, but why should a prayer that you want some innocent
person to die, why should God listen to that? Okay, maybe we
believe in general the efficacy of prayer, but really, like here's this
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and because it's not serving your interests and
you pray for him to die, God will listen to that? So
דכתיב, Dechtiv, the verse says כציפור לנוד כדרור לעוף, ke-tzippor lanud ke-deror
la'of, like a bird flies free כדרור לעוף, ke-deror la'of, like the
freedom of a bird, כן קללת חינם לא תבא, ken killat chinam
lo tavo, a meaningless curse will not come true. So you're cursing
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you want him to die, there's no
basis for that, why should God listen to that? So אמר ההוא
סבא מפרקי דרבא שמיע לי, Amar hahu saba mipirkei d'Rava shmia li,
so a certain elder said I heard from the yeshiva of רבא
Rava the answer to this. שהיה להם לבקש רחמים על דורם ולא
ביקשו. She-haya lahem levakesh rachamim al doram velo bikshu. The כהנים גדולים
Kohanim Gedolim share some of the guilt. They should have prayed for
their generation that these types of things shouldn't happen, that accidental deaths
shouldn't happen, which basically means if something bad happens the leaders have
some culpability. Now here's tying it back into prayer: they should have
prayed to God to interfere. I mean where's the בחירה חופשית? bechira
chofshit? But you could also say they should have done a better
job as religious leaders and spoken to people more about responsibility and
the sanctity of life and care that they had to take in
order to ensure that these things don't happen, which is so it
is an interesting question: why is the death of the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol set this guy free? Like what's the logic between that?
So anyway here it sort of says well maybe they do have
a little bit of culpability in that. Okay. Okay, we ended the
day by having אבימלך Avimelech as an example, and אבימלך Avimelech was
blamed for not doing דרך ארץ. derech eretz. Right. דוד המלך David
HaMelech was modeling how people act, and he caused right he caused
his people right right the leader models the right way of acting.
Exactly. ואיכא דמתני כדי שיצלו. Ve'ika d'matni kedei she'yitzalu. Now some have
the version in the mishna different. Not that they shouldn't pray that
their kids should die, but כדי שיצלו עליהם שלא ימותו, kedei she'yitzalu
aleihem shelo yamutu, to opposite you're asking them to pray that their
kids should live. That's a big ask. Okay. But so then the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, that's even worse. טעמא דמצלו, Taima d'matslu,
so the reason the כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gedolim aren't dying right now
is because these רוצחים rotzchim are praying for them to live. הא
לא מצלו, Ha lo matslu, the implication would be if they wouldn't
actively be praying for them to live, so אמאי מייתי, amai meiti,
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would die? מה הוה ליה למיעבד? Mah
hava leh lemievad? Why should the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol be deserving
of death? So הכא אמרינן, Hacha amrinan, so here we say so
and part of sharpening the question. Here in בבל, Bavel, the way
we express the irony of such a situation is by saying טוביה
חטא וזיגוד מנגד? Tuvia chata v'Zigud manged? Tuvia sinned and זיגוד Zigud
gets lashes? Like because ראובן Reuven sins and שמעון Shimon gets thrown
into jail? So where's the justice in that? Now this is based
on a case where the גמרא Gemara says that טוביה Tuvia actually
sinned, he committed some sexual sin, and this guy זיגוד Zigud went
to court and said I saw him commit this sin, and whoever
it was רבא Rava I think or whatever said to him you're
only an עד אחד. ed echad. עד אחד Ed echad isn't believed.
So if you're going around telling people this guy sinned and it's
not a testimony that's believed in court, you're just spreading לשון הרע.
lashon hara. So which is like a fascinating גמרא. Gemara. But anyway,
so where's the justice in that? The רוצח rotzeach killed and the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is deserving of death? התם אמרי אינשי Hatam
amrei inshi of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, here's the way they phrase
the irony of this. שכם נסיב ומבגאי גזיר? Shechem nasiv u'Mavgai gazir?
שכם Shechem married דינה Dinah and מבגאי Mavgai which somehow means the
members of the city or maybe it's a name of a particular
person in the city. He had to get a ברית מילה? bris
milah? Right that's the story, right? שכם Shechem makes everybody in the
city get a ברית מילה. bris milah. שכם Shechem got to have
sexual relations with this woman he wanted and I had to get
a ברית מילה? bris milah? So where's the justice? So אמר ההוא
סבא מפרזיקא מפרקי דרבא שמיע לי, Amar hahu saba mipirzika mipirkei d'Rava
shmia li, I heard this from the teaching of רבא. Rava. שהיה
להם לבקש רחמים על דורם ולא ביקשו. She-haya lahem levakesh rachamim al
doram velo bikshu. And this is even heavier than before. Not just
that the prayers will be answered, but that they start off with
a certain deserving of death when murder or even accidental death occurs
under your watch. I mean just think about things that have happened
recently of course with all those horrific shootings or whatever. Where's the
responsibility of the leaders? And so it says yeah they are to
some degree deserving of death themselves and they have to be prayed
that they don't die. כי הא Ki ha "כי הא דההוא גברא
דאכליה אריה ברחוק תלתא פרסי מיניה דרבי יהושע בן לוי". Ki ha
de-hahu gavra d'achleih aryeh berachuk telasa parsei mineih d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
There's a certain person that a lion attacked and was within three
פרסי, parsei, like three kilometers, of רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi. "ולא אישתעי אליהו בהדיה תלתא יומי". V'lo ishtayei Eliyahu bahadeih
telasa yomei. And as a result אליהו Eliyahu normally would regularly daily
speak to רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, didn't speak
to him for three days. Because presumably since it happened in his
vicinity, right, it was in the town that רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi had some authority over. So why didn't רבי
יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi trying to, you know, teach
people to make more protections against the lions, you know, and do
what part of his religious responsibility? You know, Rabbi Luft told me
that on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the rabbi of his שול shul
got up and for his main דרשה drasha on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur says, everybody needs to make sure that the batteries in their
smoke detectors are working. Which is like really interesting. If I'm the
rabbi, I have responsibility for the safety of my community, you know.
So anyway, so how did this lion attack this guy? What were
you doing to make sure those things don't happen? "אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב קללת חכם אפילו בחינם היא באה". Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav klalat chacham afilu bechinam hi ba'ah. Since we're talking about a
curse, and a "קללת חינם" klalat chinam is the חינם chinam and
חכם, chacham, a curse that's for naught, you know, God doesn't listen
to if it's not deserving, but a curse issued by a חכם
chacham even בחינם, bechinam, even if it was not deserving, because a
חכם chacham issued it, it's going to come true. "מנלן מאחיתופל". Menalan
me'Ahitophel. From אחיתופל. Ahitophel. In the famous גמרא Gemara at the time
it's also parallel in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, which unfortunately we haven't been
learning these days. At the time when דוד David was digging the
foundation of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, so "קפא תהומא", kafa tehoma,
he dug so deep to lay the foundation, not exactly sure why
he had to dig so deep, that he tapped into the underwater
depths and the water started coming up and it was going to
flood the whole world. In the, what, we've mentioned this before. Oh
right, exactly, and he wanted to touch the תהום. tehom. Exactly. And
in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it says that there was a little piece
of pottery on top of a hole. Right. And the pottery said
to דוד, David, don't remove me, it's going to, and דוד David
said, I don't care. Which is like crazy story. Anyway, exactly. So
"בעי למישטפי עלמא", ba'ei lemishtapei alma, the world was going to get
flooded because you released the power of the underwater depths. "אמר מאן
דכתיב שמא אחספא ומשדי בתהומא". Amar man d'chtiv shema achaspa u'mashdei bitehoma.
So דוד David had the solution. I'll write God's name on a
piece of pottery, which parallels the version that he took a pottery
off to remove it. I'll throw it down, it'll magically find the
hole, and because of God's name on it, it'll seal the hole
and then it'll save it. But in the course of it, God's
name will be erased because the water will wipe it away. What
was that case with the when they had that I was I
had thought about this גמרא Gemara a lot when they had that
underground oil hole that they couldn't seal up. Remember that disaster that
happened like a few years ago and Exxon and they whatever and
they couldn't figure out how to get to it and seal it
up. I said they just need that piece of pottery from דוד
המלך. David HaMelech. Anyway, so "דליקום אדוכתיה", d'leykum aduchteih, it will stay
on top of the hole. "ליכא דאמר ליה מידי", leika d'amar leih
midi, nobody could give him an answer. "אמר כל היודע דבר זה
ואינו אומרו יחנק בגרונו". Amar kol hayodeia davar zeh v'eino omro yechanek
bigrono. דוד David said, if anybody knows this and isn't going to
come forth and say, let him be choked in his throat. "נשא
אחיתופל קל וחומר בעצמו". Nasa Ahitophel kal vachomer b'atzmo. So אחיתופל Ahitophel
said, wait, let me think about it. So he made a "קל
וחומר". kal vachomer. "אמר ומה לעשות שלום בין איש לאשתו אמרה תורה
שמי שנכתב בקדושה ימחה על המים". Amar uma la'asot shalom bein ish
l'ishto amrah Torah shemi shenichtav bikdusha yimachei al hamayim. When to make
peace between husband and wife by case of סוטה, sotah, God says
you can write my name in קדושה kedusha on a parchment and
directly destroy my name and scrape it into the water. "לכל העולם
כולו לא כל שכן"? Lechol ha'olam kulo lo kol sheken? Certainly for
the sake of all the world you should be able to do
this. And the question is like, you know, with our halachic approach,
like what would be the "הוה אמינא"? hava amina? It's just a
negative prohibition, it's "פיקוח נפש", pikuach nefesh, of course you do it.
Like maybe he thought it's part of a "הפשטת שם אלקיך", hafshatat
shem elokecha, it's sort of like "עבודה זרה", avoda zara, what's "יהרג
ואל יעבור", yehareg v'al ya'avor, I don't know. Anyway, it's only a
"גרמא", grama, you know. Anyway, "אמר ליה שרי", Amar leih shari, it's
permissible. "כתב שם אחספא", Katav shem achaspa, so he wrote the name
on a piece of pottery, "שדי בתהומא", shadi bitehoma, he threw it
down, "נחת וקם אדוכתיה", nachat vekam aduchteih, the water went down and
it stood on its place. The other part of the story is
said he said fifteen like the water went so far down and
then he and then there was not enough water in the world
because it wasn't close to the surface and he had to say
the fifteen "שיר המעלות" Shir HaMa'alot to bring the water closer to
the surface. There's more of the story. Anyway, so this was the
"קללת חינם" klalat chinam because he only said if you don't tell
me, and אחיתופל Ahitophel told him. It also seems that אחיתופל Ahitophel
himself didn't know it until he felt the pressure to figure it
out, right, it wasn't like he knew it and was willingly withholding
it. So even though it was a "קללת חינם", klalat chinam, "וכתיב",
v'chtiv, and nevertheless it says, "ואחיתופל ראה כי לא נעשתה עצתו", v'Ahitophel
ra'ah ki lo ne'estah atzato, his, you know, counsel was not followed
in terms of the whole thing about the whole succession, "ויחבוש את
החמור ויקם וילך אל ביתו אל עירו", vayachavosh et hachamor vayakam vayeilech
el beito el iro, and he went to his city, "ויצו אל
ביתו ויחנק", vayevatz el beito vayechanek, and he gave final, final instructions
and he choked and died. Okay, seemingly like he did it to
himself. Anyway, "אמר רבי אבהו קללת חכם אפילו על תנאי היא באה".
Amar Rabbi Abbahu klalat chacham afilu al tnai hi ba'ah. It comes
even on a condition. Well, that's sort of the case of דוד,
David, he said it on condition. If you know and don't tell.
מנלן? Minalan? מאלי? Mei-Eli? דקאמר ליה עלי לשמואל. De-Kamar Lei Eli Le-Shmuel.
עלי Eli said to שמואל, Shmuel, כה יעשה לך אלהים וכה יוסיף,
Koh Ya'aseh Lecha Elokim Ve-Choh Yosif, so should God do to you
and so should God increase, אם תכחד ממני דבר, Im Techached Mimeni
Davar, if you withhold from me this thing. And then שמואל Shmuel
told him what he wanted to know. So ואף על גב דכתיב,
Ve-Af Al Gav De-Chitiv, ויגד לו שמואל את כל הדברים ולא כחד
ממנו, Vayaged Lo Shmuel Et Kol Ha-Devarim Ve-Lo Kiched Mimenu, that שמואל
Shmuel told him and did not hold it back, so the curse
should not have been fulfilled. אפילו הכי כתיב, Afilu Hachi Ketiv, but
it says by שמואל, Shmuel, ולא הלכו בניו בדרכיו, Ve-Lo Halchu Banav
Bi-Drachav, שמואל'ס Shmuel's children did not follow his ways and they took
bribes and that very much parallels what happened with עלי'ס Eli's children.
עלי'ס Eli's children also abused their authority and they took bribes and
so on. Okay, so when עלי Eli said to שמואל Shmuel God
should do to you, the implication was do to you like what
happened to me. You should also have kids that don't follow your
way. And even though it was on a תנאי, Tnai, nevertheless it
came true. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav,
נידוי על תנאי, Nidui Al Tnai, which just shows how careful you
have to be about your words. נידוי על תנאי, Nidui Al Tnai,
putting somebody in חרם Cherem on a תנאי, Tnai, צריך הפרה, Tzarich
Hafarah, even though it's on a תנאי, Tnai, you need to release
the חרם, Cherem, the נידוי, Nidui, even if the תנאי Tnai was
not satisfied. מנלן מיהודה, Minalan Mi-Yehuda, by יהודה, Yehuda, דכתיב, De-Chitiv, אם
לא הביאותיו אליך והצגתיו לפניך וחטאתי לאבי כל הימים, Im Lo Heviotiv
Elecha Ve-Hatzagtiv Lefanecha Ve-Chatati Le-Avi Kol Ha-Yamim, when he says by בנימין
Binyamin right if I don't bring בנימין Binyamin back to you I
will sin to you the whole day. So that's like considered like
נידוי Nidui to be considered to be outcast and a sinner, right?
So he's accepting it's read as accepting a חרם Cherem on himself
but only if he doesn't produce בנימין. Binyamin. Okay, now if you
think about it, here's a question. Did יהודה Yehuda fulfill that? In
a way יהודה Yehuda did fulfill that. He never brought בנימין Binyamin
back and presented him to יעקב. Yaakov. יעקב Yaakov came down to
מצרים. Mitzrayim. But the גמרא Gemara still understands that look more or
less he fulfilled it. He ensured the safety of בנימין. Binyamin. And
nevertheless, how do we know that this curse that he said about
himself וחטאתי לך Ve-Chatati Lecha like I'll be considered a sinner which
is read as a חרם, Cherem, how do we know that it
took hold? Because it says, ואמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי
יונתן, Ve-Amar Rabi Shmuel Bar Nachmani Amar Rabi Yonatan, מאי דכתיב, Mai
De-Chitiv, what's meant by the verse יחי ראובן ואל ימות וזאת ליהודה?
Yechi Reuven Ve-Al Yamot Ve-Zot Li-Yehuda? What's the juxtaposition when משה Moshe
in the ברכה Beracha says let ראובן Reuven live and not die
and then he says וזאת ליהודה? Ve-Zot Li-Yehuda? Okay and part of
the question is that it doesn't introduce the ברכה Beracha of יהודה
Yehuda by saying ליהודה אמר. Li-Yehuda Amar. By all the other tribes
it says ליוסף אמר, Le-Yosef Amar, לבנימין אמר, Le-Binyamin Amar, but יהודה
Yehuda it just says וזאת ליהודה. Ve-Zot Li-Yehuda. So it's directly juxtaposed
to that of ראובן. Reuven. So כל אותן ארבעים שנה שהיו ישראל
במדבר, Kol Otan Arbaim Shana She-Hayu Yisrael Ba-Midbar, the whole 40 years,
עצמותיו של יהודה היו מגולגלים בארון. Atzmotav Shel Yehuda Hayu Megulgalim Ba-Aron.
The bones of יהודה Yehuda were rolling around in the ארון, Aron,
sort of showing that his soul was not at rest. עד שאמר
משה ביקש עליו רחמים, Ad She-Amar Moshe Bikaish Alav Rachamim, until משה
Moshe prayed for him. אמר לפניו ריבונו של עולם, Amar Lefanav Ribono
Shel Olam, מי גרם לראובן שיודה? Mi Garam Le-Reuven She-Yodeh? Who caused
ראובן Reuven to admit his sin with בלהה? Bilhah? So that was
יהודה. Yehuda. So it was יהודה Yehuda because מדת הדין Midat Ha-Din
in the פסוקים, Pesukim, but they say that since יהודה Yehuda made
a public admission of his sin, the reading is that that caused
ראובן Reuven also to make a public admission of his sin. So
וזאת ליהודה, Ve-Zot Li-Yehuda, is this worthy of יהודה Yehuda the fate
that has occurred to ראובן? Reuven? So after he said יחי ראובן
ואל ימות, Yechi Reuven Ve-Al Yamot, ראובן Reuven live you know eternally
and ראובן Reuven did תשובה, Teshuvah, וזאת ליהודה, Ve-Zot Li-Yehuda, is this
the fate that יהודה Yehuda deserves? שמע השם קול יהודה, Shma Hashem
Kol Yehuda, God listen to his voice, allow his soul to find
rest. עלו איבריו לשפה, Alu Eivrav Le-Shafe, so the bones reconnected, they
went into their sockets. So rather than being like the big pile
of bones rolling around, you had a full skeleton now. Okay so
at least his bones were at rest. ולא הוו קא מעיילי ליה
במתיבתא דרקיעא, Ve-Lo Havu Ka Ma'aylei Lei Bi-Metivta De-Rakia, but they still
wouldn't let יהודה'ס Yehuda's soul enter into the ישיבה Yeshiva up in
heaven. So ואל עמו תביאנו, Ve-El Amo Tevieu, so we keep on
reading the פסוק, Pasuk, bring him to his nation. So they let
him come into the ישיבה. Yeshiva. לא הוה קא ידע למישקל ומיטרח
בשמעתא, Lo Hava Ka Yada Li-Mishkal U-Mitrach Bi-Shmata, but he didn't know
how to argue in you know have good you know arguments in
Talmudic discussion בהדי רבנן Bahadei Rabanan with the other rabbis up there
in the ישיבה Yeshiva in heaven. ידיו רב לו, Yadav Rav Lo,
let his hand be mighty, let him be able to be you
know have strength in these sort of in the Talmudic debates. לא
הוה ידע לפרוקי קושיא, Lo Hava Yada Lifrokei Kushya, fine he was
able to debate well but he couldn't answer questions he couldn't really
resolve things. ועזר מצריו תהיה, Ve-Eizer Mi-Tzarav Tihyeh, let him have help
from his from his oppressors. Okay, איבעיא להו, Ibaia Lehu, now fine
so that's the end of that story about you know that יהודה
Yehuda but תוספות Tosafot asks an important question. תוספות Tosafot says one
minute because a primary way in the Middle Ages that the rabbinic
leaders got people to follow their edicts was if you don't follow
our edicts you are going to be what? Put in חרם, Cherem,
right like חרם דרבינו גרשום. Cherem De-Rabeinu Gershom. But here's the problem.
If I say if you don't do this I'm going to put
you in חרם, Cherem, well then everybody's in חרם Cherem because you
know because even on תנאי Tnai it somehow takes effect and has
to be released. So תוספות Tosafot is bothered about that. So תוספות
Tosafot says no there's a difference. He says יהודה Yehuda when he
said if I don't return him to you that wasn't under his
control. And since it wasn't under his control how did he know
right יוסף Yosef could have. whatever, right? So because it wasn't under
his control, it took effect regardless, because he was, but as long
as the condition of the חרם cherem is completely something you can
control, then it's not it won't take effect unless you actually satisfy
the conditions. Okay, but this גמרא Gemara creates real important halachic and
authority issues for the ראשונים Rishonim in the Middle Ages who used
a חרם על תנאי cherem al tnai as a way of of
gaining compliance. So just to see the question in תוספות Tosfos he
says אפילו על תנאי צריך הפרה, afillu al tnai tzarich hafara, יש
מדקדקים מכאן דנידויים שלנו, yesh medakdekim mikan deniduim shelanu, our נידויים, niduim,
our חרמים, cherems, אפילו אותם שיש להם זמן, afillu osam sheyesh lahem
zman, even if they first of all let's say they're time limits
to them, אין להוציא עצמן מספק, ein lehosei atzman misafek, שהרי הכי
התנה בדבר שלא היה בידו לקיים sheharei hachi hitna bedavar shelo hayah
beyado lekayem and so okay, so it won't work. And then תוספות's
Tosfos's answer like the text is a little bit needs fixing here,
but it basically is no, הכא התנה בדבר שלא היה בידו לקיים.
hacha hitna bedavar shelo hayah beyado lekayem. Here יהודה Yehudah couldn't control
it. דשמא היה מעכב יוסף deshema hayah me'akev Yosef או נגנב או
אבד בדרך. o nignav o avad baderech. ולכך חל מעיקרא גם נידוי
על תנאי. ulekach chal me'ikra gam nidui al tnai. That's why it
took effect even though it was on condition, because it wasn't a
condition you could control. So it took effect regardless. אבל שאר תנאים
דבידו לקיים, aval shear tna'im devyado lekayem, but other ones that the
person can choose is he going to do the you know do
the things that's going to lead to the חרם, cherem, כגון שמנדית
אדם שלא יעשה הדבר, kegon shemandis adam shelo ya'aseh hadavar, that you
put a person on the חרם cherem and you say if you
do so and so then you're going to be put in חרם.
cherem. Okay, ואזי לא חל הנידוי כלל מעיקרו. va'azei lo chal hanidui
klal me'ikro. That's not going to take effect from the outset. It
will only take effect when the condition is met. דכיון דבידו הוא
משעת הנידוי אנו יודעים בבודאי שלא בדעתו לעשות הדבר, dekivan devyado hu
mis'as hanidui anu yodim bevada'i shelo bedato la'asos hadavar, because then we
can presume that since he can control it that he's not he
doesn't want to be put in חרם, cherem, so therefore it's not
going to take effect at the beginning, it'll only take effect if
and when he chooses to actually violate the conditions. Okay, but that's
very important because that was a major tool that they used in
the Middle Ages. All right, let's finish up here. So now we
have one halachic question left. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, they asked a
question. במיתת כולן הוא חוזר או דילמא במיתת אחד מהן. bimisas kulan
hu chozer o dilma bimisas echad mehen. When we said that there
are all these כהנים גדולים, kohanim gedolim, so do you need all
of them to die if there's a period when there are multiple
כהנים גדולים, kohanim gedolim, an ex-כהן גדול, kohen gadol, a sitting כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, is any the death of any one of them
free the free the person or do all of them have to
be died? So תא שמע ta shma come and hear, you would
assume it means any one of them. תא שמע נגמר דינו בלא
כהן גדול אינו יוצא משם לעולם. ta shma nigmar dino belo kohen
gadol eino yosei misham le'olam. It says if somebody's rule is passed
without a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, he's never freed. Now why not?
So there's not a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, but what about the
other כהנים גדולים, kohanim gedolim, why wouldn't they free him? So that's
not a question. וימותו ליהדר בהדי הנהו, veyamusu liyahdar bahadi hanhu, why
isn't he freed with the other כהנים גדולים? kohanim gedolim? So he
needs the answer. דליכא. deleka. No, there aren't other כהנים גדולים. kohanim
gedolim. It's not all the time that you have multiple כהנים גדולים.
kohanim gedolim. But when you do have multiple ones, the question is
do you need all of them to die or not. Let's just
read the משנה mishna so we can get a little bit closer
a little to to where we should be. Okay, מי שנגמר דינו,
mi shenigmar dino, this is the line we just quoted anyway, מת
כהן גדול. mes kohen gadol. Now if when does a כהן גדול's
kohen gadol's death free the guy? Does he have to already be
in the עיר מקלט? ir miklat? So the משנה mishna says no.
Once his once the דין din was done and בית דין beis
din פסקן pasken and said fine, you killed the guy, you're found
guilty, but it was בשוגג, beshogeg, you have to go to the
עיר מקלט. ir miklat. That's your הלכה. halacha. By the way, that's
interesting that there's a concept of גמר דין gmar din to go
to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, right? It's not just you run
and you're protected. Like this is again the בית דין beis din
taking over. The בית דין beis din passes its judgment, its sentencing
to you, and it is that you go to the עיר מקלט.
ir miklat. So once that גמר דין gmar din occurred, then the
person is liable to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, then the death
of the כהן גדול kohen gadol would free him. הרי זה אינו
גולה. harei zeh eino goleh. אם עד שלא נגמר דינו מת כהן
גדול, im ad shelo nigmar dino mes kohen gadol, but if the
כהן גדול kohen gadol died during the proceedings before the גמר דין
gmar din ומינו אחר תחתיו, uminu acher tachtav, but then they created
a new כהן גדול kohen gadol during the proceedings ואחר כך נגמר
דינו, ve'achar kach nigmar dino, and then he had a גמר דין,
gmar din, חוזר במיתתו של שני, chozer bimaso shel sheni, then it's
the death of the second one. Okay, so as long as there
is a כהן גדול kohen gadol when his גמר דין gmar din
occurs, so at the moment of his גמר דין, gmar din, you
look who's a כהן גדול kohen gadol is and when that כהן
גדול kohen gadol dies, he goes free. Now what if there's no
sitting no כהן גדול kohen gadol at the moment of גמר דין?
gmar din? Okay, so נגמר דינו בלא כהן גדול, nigmar dino belo
kohen gadol, so this is the one case we right which is
which we don't know, if there's no sitting כהן גדול kohen gadol
והורג כהן גדול, ve'horeg kohen gadol, now not only that, let's say
somebody kills a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Okay, and then by the
time of his גמר דין gmar din there's a new כהן גדול.
kohen gadol. Okay, so כהן גדול שהרג, kohen gadol sheharag, like כהן
גדול kohen gadol committed murder and the time of his גמר דין
gmar din there's a new כהן גדול. kohen gadol. All those three
cases אינו יוצא משם לעולם, eino yosei misham le'olam, they never go
free. So the last two you sort of understand, right? But anyway,
but the the first one was the end of the point we
made before, that it's the death of the כהן גדול kohen gadol
who is around at the moment of גמר דין gmar din and
if by pure luck happens or chance happens that there's no כהן
גדול kohen gadol around at the moment of גמר דין, gmar din,
then you don't have the the conditions necessary for Understand, right? But
anyway, but the first one was the end of the point we
made before, that it's the death of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
who is around at the moment of the גמר דין. Gmar Din.
If by pure luck happens or chance happens that there's no כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol around at the moment of the גמר דין, Gmar
Din, then you don't have the conditions necessary for ever going free.
Okay, the אינו יוצא, eino yotze, now, when he says he can't
leave going back to being in the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, he
can't leave לא לעדות מצוה, lo l'edut mitzvah, not to give testimony
even that's an even that's for the sake of a מצוה, mitzvah,
ולא לעדות ממון v'lo l'edut mamon or testimony for a monetary dispute,
ולא לעדות נפשות v'lo l'edut nefashot or testimony even for a capital
crime. Now the question is why maybe בית דין Beit Din should
go there and you know and have the court case there to
receive his testimony, but regardless, he can't go out for any reason.
ואפילו שצריכים לו, v'afilu shetzrichim lo, even if he's needed to serve
a public service, ואפילו שר צבא ישראל כיואב בן צרויה, v'afilu Sar
Tzva Yisrael k'Yoav ben Zeruiah, they're at war and they need him
as a to head an army. Now of course that's a real
big question, right? Because okay, there's a negative prohibition of not leaving,
but like what happens to פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh like the discussion
earlier, right? You have a war, your security? I mean that's a
very strange הלכה. halacha. משום לא לא, mishum lo lo, שנאמר אשר
נס שמה, shene'emar asher nas shama, there. שם תהא דירתו, sham tehei
dirato, there he must remain. שם תהא מיתתו, sham tehei mitato, there
he must die, assuming the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol doesn't die first.
שם תהא קבורתו, sham tehei kevurato, there he shall be buried. Now
last point, כשם שעיר קולטת כך תחום קולט. keshem she'ir koletet kach
tchum kolet. So running in your way running there we discussed whether
you'd be protected, but but at the city itself we say now
not only the city but its environs. Now what defines the edge
the scope of its environs? ורצוח שיצא חוץ לתחום, v'rotzeach sheyatza chutz
latchum, it means the two thousand אמות, amot, that's the תחום שבת.
tchum Shabbat. ורצוח שיצא חוץ לתחום ומצאו גואל הדם, v'rotzeach sheyatza chutz
latchum umatz'o Goel HaDam, now finally the question, there he is, he's
exposed, he's out of the city, he's not protected, the גואל הדם.
Goel HaDam. What is the we know the גואל הדם Goel HaDam
is not liable for killing him. Okay, should he kill him or
shouldn't he kill him? סו רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר מצוה ביד גואל
הדם, so Rabbi Yose HaGelili omer mitzvah beyad Goel HaDam, is a
מצוה mitzvah in the hand of the גואל הדם, Goel HaDam, the
גואל הדם Goel HaDam should kill him actually if he goes outside
of the עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. ורשות ביד כל אדם, v'reshut beyad
kol adam, and any normal person is allowed to kill him. Okay,
so רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it's really very strange. I mean at
the end of the guy this guy did בשוגג. beshogeg. That will
keep the guy in the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, so you could
read רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose maybe less that the guy is deserving
of death and more that he he must stay in the עיר
מקלט Ir Miklat like he has an obligation to stay. So if
he's really his life is at serious risk when he leaves, this
is going to keep him in the עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, but
it still it sounds more than that and it's very it's troublesome,
right? He killed בשוגג, beshogeg, why is there a מצוה ביד גואל
הדם? mitzvah beyad Goel HaDam? רבי עקיבא אומר רשות ביד גואל הדם
וכל אדם חייבין עליו. Rabbi Akiva omer reshut beyad Goel HaDam v'chol
adam chayavin alav. And here's a question how to read the last
line of the משנה. Mishnah. No, the גואל הדם Goel HaDam does
not have a מצוה. mitzvah. Maybe the תורה Torah allows it and
that's, you know, I would think the פשט pshat of the תורה
Torah is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva not just because of my own,
you know, ethical instincts, it seems like the פסוקים psukim are saying
this. They don't want the גואל הדם Goel HaDam to kill him,
right? As the פסוקים psukim seem to be saying. So רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says fine, they will not hold him liable, the גואל
הדם, Goel HaDam, that'll keep the guy in the עיר מקלט Ir
Miklat and maybe the תורה Torah can't totally eradicate these elements of
vigilante justice so it has to tolerate it to a small degree,
okay, but it's only a רשות, reshut, there's no purpose, there's no
point, there's no מצוה mitzvah to kill him. And let's say somebody
not the גואל הדם Goel HaDam kills him. So there's two ways
to read the last line in the משנה. Mishnah. One is any
other person who kills the who kills him is liable, has committed
murder, that's our version, but some have the גירסא, girsa, אין חייבין
עליו, ein chayavin alav, that everybody else doesn't have a doesn't have
permission to kill to kill him, but if they did, it would
not be considered murder. Okay, so that also I think remains troublesome
to think about that, okay? But so this end is a very
fascinating about this issue about how much is the תורה Torah really
against this vigilante justice and just tolerating it in small degrees and
how much is it actually saying actually there's some value to this
and there remains some מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so we'll end with this
and continue with the גמרא Gemara tomorrow.